(upbeat music)
- Hello English learners,
welcome back to
English, odd, my name
is Marco, and I'm Erika.
- And today we have a great lesson
for all our upper intermediate students.
- That's right, we're talking
about airplane travel today.
- Airplane travel, right.
- So we're gonna be
in an airplane basically.
- And we're gonna be listening
to some of the common things
you might hear on an
announcement in the airplane.
- Yeah, usually the flight attendant or
the captain will come on and say something
and well, usually it's in English, so we
gotta understand what they're saying.
- That's right, and we'll
also learn some great phrases
that you can use when
you wanna describe flights
to your friends, when
you're talking to them.
- Yeah, that always happens.
You arrive somewhere and people
are like, hey, how was your flight?
Now you know how to answer it.
- Exactly.
- Okay, so why don't we take a
look at our vocabulary preview?
- Very vocabulary preview.
- Well, we've got three words for you here
in vocabulary preview all about flying.
- Okay, so what's our first one?
- Turbulence. - Turbulence.
- Turbulence.
So, turbulence, how can we describe this?
- Well, turbulence when
you're in an airplane,
basically is air that is moving
in all directions really fast.
- Okay, so what happens?
- So the airplane will
start to shake, right?
- Yep.
- It's the same thing,
if you're flying a kite
and maybe some turbulence is in the air,
your kite will maybe fall to the ground.
- Oh, yeah.
- So it's air that's moving in all
directions, it's really turbulent.
- All right, well, we'll hear
how this word is used in
the dialogue, but another
airplane word, we hear a lot.
Crew, crew, flight, crew.
- Yes.
- C-R-E-W, crew.
So the flight crew is
basically the team, right?
- Yep.
- It's all the people
that are in the airplane.
So it's basically
the captain or in the
co-pilot and all the
flight attendants, right?
- Exactly, yep.
- That's the flight crew.
- Yes.
- Okay, and what about our last word?
- Bumpy ride.
- A bumpy ride.
- Bumpy.
- Not smooth.
- Yeah.
- So what would be an
example of a bumpy ride?
- Okay, imagine if you're driving
in your car and you're driving
on a dirt road, like with
many holes in it and everything.
- And rocks, yes.
- You're driving on that road and
it would be really, really bumpy.
- Right, so your car will be moving a lot.
- And shaking.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Bumpy ride is a trip where
you move and shake a lot.
It's kind of uncomfortable.
- So you can say that is a bumpy road.
- Or it was a bumpy ride.
- It was a bumpy ride.
- Yeah.
- Okay, so now let's
listen to our dialogue.
We're gonna be listening to these people
on an airplane and the captain
is gonna give some instructions.
(upbeat music)
- And the next thing you know, we're
running towards the, oh, did you feel that?
- Yeah, don't worry about it.
We're just going through
a bit of turbulence.
- Ladies and gentlemen,
this is your captain speaking.
It looks like we've hit
a patch of rough air.
So we're going to have a bit of a
bumpy ride for the next several minutes.
- This is why I hate flying.
- At this time, I'd like to
remind up our passengers
to fasten their seat
belts and remain seated
until the fasten seat
belt sign is turned off.
Please ensure that
all cabin baggage is
carefully stowed under
the seat in front of you.
I'll be back to update you in a minute.
- Did you hear that?
Oh my God, Brent!
- Don't worry about it.
This is totally normal.
It happens all that.
- Ladies and gentlemen,
this is your captain again.
We've got quite a large
patch of rough air ahead of us.
And so for your safety, we will
be suspending in flight service.
I would ask all the in flight crew
to return to their seat at this time.
I would also ask that all our passengers
are afraid for using the lavatory
until the seat belt sign
has been switched off.
We can expect.
(dramatic music)
- Well, here we are
with another dramatic
dialogue, another
explosion in English vlog.
What's happening?
I don't know, a lot of
adventure is going on.
So we'll see what happens.
But I'm sure they're all right.
Don't worry, everyone, I'm sure.
- Well, I hope so.
It's kind of making me
nervous for my next flight.
- All right.
So let's take a look at some of the words
that the captain used in language takeaway.
- Language takeaway.
- All right, all of these words, you'll hear
really, really often when you're flying.
And the first one we have for
you is fast and fast and fastened.
Fasten your seat belt.
- Mm-hmm.
- Now this is a great word.
Fasten means to do up,
do up or put on or connect.
- Connect, right.
- So usually it'll be with a seat belt
or a belt or something like that, right?
- Now the pronunciation
here is interesting.
- Yes.
- It's spelled F-A-S-T-E-N.
- Right, so it would be fast and no.
- No, right.
- Fasten.
- Fasten, the T kind of becomes silent.
So it's fastened.
- Yep, okay.
Let's look at our next word, lavatory.
- Lavatory.
Okay, so what is lavatory exactly?
'Cause I'm always confused.
What's the difference between bathroom,
restroom, washroom, W-C, lavatory?
- I know, so many words for bathroom.
Lavatory is a room with
a toilet and sink only.
- Only a toilet and sink, so no bathtub.
- No, no shower either.
- No shower.
- So it's very, very common to find a
lavatory in boats, airplanes, or in trains.
- Yep, but never in your house.
- Never in your house.
- Even if your room
in your house is only a
sink in a toilet, it's
still not a lavatory.
- It's a bathroom.
- Yeah, okay.
- I don't know why.
That's just the way it is in English.
- And something interesting
that you told me today, W-C,
that's the common thing
that you'll see on a bathroom.
- Yep.
- What does that stand for?
- Water closet.
- Yep, wow, I didn't know that.
- Yeah.
- Water closet.
Okay, anyways, let's take
a look at our next word.
Stow, stow, to stow.
- Yes, stow your luggage.
- So your luggage.
So if I stow my luggage, it means--
- You put it in a place where you
can get it easily, but it is very safe.
- Maybe it's not even visible, right?
- Yeah, so you put it away in a safe spot.
- Okay, so usually in airplanes,
they will tell you to stow
your luggage under your seat.
- Yes, or stow your
luggage in the overhead bin.
- Overhead bin or overhead compartment?
- Yes.
- Okay, and our last word.
- Refrain.
Refrain from doing something.
- So this is a verb, meaning avoid doing.
- Avoid doing, do not do.
- Exactly.
- Something interesting
about this grammar wise
is it's usually followed
by from-- - Yeah.
- Refrain from, and the verb
that follows is always jarring, right?
- Yeah, so refrain from, I-N-G.
- Right.
- Refrain from, using the lavatory.
- Yes, refrain from smoking.
- Refrain from smoking, okay.
So refrain from.
- Yep.
- All right, so some really great examples
in language takeaway, and
well, now let's take a look
at fluency builder and see
some of these great phrases.
- Fluency builder.
- All right, three phrases we have for
you here, and the first one remain seated.
- Remain seated.
- So to remain seated.
- Really simple to stay sitting.
- To stay on your seat, don't stand up.
- Yes.
- This is really important
in airplanes, right?
- Yeah, because otherwise,
if there's turbulence,
you could, you know, end
up flying around the airplane.
- A fall, exactly, and hurt yourself.
- Remain seated.
- Now, one of the reasons
they had to remain seated
was because they were going to
go through a patch of rough air.
- Patch of rough air.
So patch.
- Now, interesting, okay.
So patch is a small area, right?
- Yeah, yeah, so a
small area of turbulence.
- A small area of turbulence.
Now, what would be
another example of patch?
- Maybe a patch of strawberries.
- So it's like a little
strawberry garden, right?
- Yes, or a patch of grass.
- Patch of grass,
usually in front of your
house, you'll have a
little patch of grass.
- Yep.
- Okay, so patch of, and
now our last phrase, suspend.
- Suspend.
- Suspend in flight service.
- Yeah, so stop for a short time.
Stop for a short time.
So you could suspend your work.
- Yeah, and if you're going on vacation,
you could suspend your
subscription to the newspaper.
- Mm-hmm.
- Okay, so suspend to temporarily stop.
- Yes.
- Okay, so we've covered a lot of
vocabulary and some great phrases.
So why don't we listen
to our dialogue one more
time and we'll come
back and talk about flying.
(upbeat music)
- And the next thing you know, we're
running towards the, oh, did you feel that?
- Yeah, don't worry about it.
We're just going through
a bit of turbulence.
- Ladies and gentlemen,
this is your captain speaking.
It looks like we've hit
a patch of rough air,
so we're going to have a bit of a
bumpy ride for the next several minutes.
- This is why I hate flying.
- At this time, I'd like to
remind all our passengers
to fasten their seat
belts and remain seated
until the fasten seat
belt sign is turned off.
Please ensure that
all cabin baggage is
carefully stowed under
the seat in front of you.
I'll be back to update you in a minute.
- Did you hear that?
Oh my God, Brent.
- Don't worry about it.
This is totally normal.
It happens all that, mmm.
- Ladies and gentlemen,
this is your captain again.
We've got quite a large patch
of rough air ahead of us, and
so for your safety, we will
be suspending in flight service.
I would ask all the inflight crew
to return to their seats at this time.
I would also ask that all our passengers
are afraid for using the lavatory
until the seat belt sign
has been switched off.
We can expect.
(dramatic music)
- Erica, have you ever had
a turbulent flight like this?
- No, never this bad, a
little bit of turbulence.
Actually, I kind of like
turbulent flight, why?
It's sort of like, I don't know, it's
kind of fine, you get shaken around,
you're like stomach moves up
and down, and you're like nervous.
- No, I get a little excited.
Well, it is true that flying is
actually very, very safe, right?
- Yeah, I know we all hear that more people
are killed in car accidents
than flight accidents.
So it's very, very safe.
So yeah, I don't worry
about the turbulence.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Not on wood.
- Yeah, so flying is really safe,
and as long as you remain seated,
you fasten your seatbelt,
and you follow the
instructions, you shouldn't
have any problems.
- Yeah, yeah, actually that's a
really good point, 'cause actually
when I was reading about
flight turbulence for this dialogue,
I kept reading all these
stories about these people
who, when they got into some turbulence
air were knocked over or they ended up
like actually literally flying through
the cabin and getting really badly hurt.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Everyone, you got
to fasten your seatbelt.
- Yes, remain seated.
- Yeah, flying tips here at English Pause.
- Flying tips at English Pause,
we don't want you to get hurt.
And we know that you
travel, that's so be safe, right?
- Yeah, and use this language
to describe your flight.
- Okay, so come to
our website, EnglishPod.
com where you can leave questions,
you can also leave your comments.
- Yeah, Marco and I are always there,
and actually, in fact, we
have to go check the site now.
So, yeah, we're out of time,
so we'll see you guys next time.
- Thanks for listening, bye.
(upbeat music)